Jascha Heifetz Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Jascha Heifetz Collection1802-1987 (bulk 1911-1974)
ML31.H4
Heifetz, Jascha, 1901-1987
circa 17,500 items 280 boxes 52 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The collection includes Heifetz's personal music library of original compositions, arrangements, and transcriptions (some of which are unpublished), his annotated parts and scores, holographs and manuscripts of many of his contemporaries, and hundreds of printed scores. Concert programs document his performances from 1911 to 1974, and photographs, photo albums, and scrapbooks, encompassing the violinist's entire life. The correspondence, constituting a small part of the collection, contains letters from such important musical figures of the 20th century as Leopold Auer, Benjamin Britten, Sergei Prokofiev, George Bernard Shaw, and Sir William Walton; correspondence from Heifetz is also housed in other Music Division collections.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Auer, Leopold, 1845-1930--Correspondence.; Britten, Benjamin, 1913-1976--Correspondence.; Heifetz, Jascha, 1901-1987--Autographs.; Heifetz, Jascha, 1901-1987--Correspondence.; Heifetz, Jascha, 1901-1987--Portraits.; Heifetz, Jascha, 1901-1987.; Heifetz, Jascha, 1901-1987.; Prokofiev, Sergey, 1891-1953--Correspondence.; Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950--Correspondence.; Walton, William, 1902-1983--Correspondence.
Subjects
Musicians--Correspondence.
Titles
Heifetz collection, 1802-1987
Administrative Information
Provenance
Deposit; Jascha Heifetz; 1952.
Deposit; Myra C. Livingston; 1991.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
Sound recordings were transferred to the Library of Congress Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division.
Related Material
Some books were transferred to the Library of Congress general Music Division collections.
Biographical Sketch
Date Event
1901 Feb. 2 Born in Vilna (Vilnius), Lithuania
1904 First violin lessons with father, Ruvim (Reuven)
1910 Admitted to St. Petersburg Conservatory; begins studies with Leopold Auer
1912 May 24 Berlin recital debut
1912 Oct. 28 Berlin Philharmonic debut under Arthur Nikisch, performing Tchaikovsky Violin Concerto
1917 June 27 Leaves for New York
1917 Oct. 27 Carnegie Hall debut
1917 Nov. Makes first recordings, for Victor records
1920 May 5 London debut, Queen's Hall
1921 Tours Australia and New Zealand
1923 Tours Far East; purchases Guarneri del Gesu violin
1925 Becomes an American citizen
1926 Tours Palestine
1928 Marries Florence Vidor
1930 First child, Josepha, born
1931 Radio debut
1932 Second child, Robert, born
1934 Tours Russia for the first and last time after immigrating to the United States
1938 Stars in Samuel Goldwyn film "They Shall Have Music"
1939 Dec. 7 Premieres concerto by William Walton in Cleveland under Artur Rodzinski
1940 Tours South America
1941-45 Performs at American military bases, completing three overseas tours for USO campshows
1945 Divorced from Florence Vidor
1946 Marries Frances Spiegelberg
1947 Takes two-year sabbatical from concert performance; continues to record
1948 Joseph (Jay) born to Frances and Jascha Heifetz
1949 Jan. Returns to concert stage
1951 Acquires "Dolphin" Stradivarius
1952 Feb. 28 Deposits collection of music and correspondence at the Library of Congress
1953 Apr. 16 Attacked following Jerusalem recital, apparently for having performed the Richard Strauss violin sonata
1956 Curtails concert appearances
1960 Forms duo with cellist Gregor Piatigorsky
1962 Begins teaching at the University of Southern California
1972 Final recordings made
1972 Oct. 23 Final public concert presented
1975 "Heifetz Collection," a 5-volume 30-disc set, released by RCA
1987 Dec. 10 Dies in Los Angeles
Scope and Content Note
The Jascha Heifetz Collection, in the breadth and variety of its contents, gives a rare and comprehensive look at the life of one of history's most important violinists. Heifetz's personal music library includes his original compositions, arrangements and transcriptions (some of which are unpublished), his annotated parts and scores, holographs and manuscripts of many of his contemporaries, and hundreds of printed scores (at least some of which appear to have been previously owned by Joseph Achron). Concert programs document his performances from 1911 to 1974, and photographs, photo albums, and scrapbooks, encompassing the violinist's entire life, capture Heifetz in performance, with his family, and with notable personalities. And the correspondence, constituting a small part of the collection, contains letters from such important musical figures of the twentieth-century as Leopold Auer, Benjamin Britten, Sergei Prokofiev, George Bernard Shaw, and Sir William Walton.
The Music has been further divided into four subseries:
1. Compositions by Heifetz
2. Arrangements and Editions by Heifetz
3. Other Composers
4. Lists and Catalogs
In using the guide to the Music, the following distinctions should be observed. Bracketed titles are uniform titles, assigned in accordance with Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules, second edition. Non-bracketed titles are shown as they appear on the music itself. Numbers in parentheses refer to the number of copies. Where no contrary information is give, music may be assumed to be printed. All of Heifetz's compositions, with the exception of the cadenzas and Theme and Variations, were published under the pseudonym of Jim Hoyl.
The rest of the materials in the collection are divided into five series:
Programs
Correspondence
Photographs
Scrapbooks
Miscellaneous and Realia
There are approximately 2,000 items in the Programs subseries. The majority of these are concert and recital programs dating from Heifetz's 1917 Carnegie Hall debut to his last concerts in 1974. The remainder consists of programs of Heifetz's radio appearances (and often the scripts for these shows), program files, and a program notebook. The program files, arranged alphabetically by performance location (city or country), although headings also exist under "Radio" and "Repertoire," contain typescript concert and recital programs as well as typescript and manuscript repertoire lists. The program notebook lists programs of receitals given by Heifetz in the United States and Canada between 1930 and 1956; these programs are arranged alphabetically by city. The researcher using the Programs subseries should further note that encores are often listed in the program files and in the program notebook, and that duplicate and additional Heifetz programs can be found in the scrapbooks in the Jascha Heifetz Collection and in the general collections of the Music Division.
The items in the Correspondence subseries are arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Except where noted, letters are to Heifetz. A few letters are kept with musical scores, but are cross-referenced in the Correspondence subseries.
The scrapbooks and photograph albums have been left intact. Size, rather than date order, was used as the organizing principal for these items, as many of them contain unusually large date spans that frequently overlap. Although an attempt has been made to provide date ranges under the titles (where they occur) of the scrapbooks, these are not to be considered definitive because so much material is either undated or in foreign languages.
Books from Mr. Heifetz's library have been treated in several different ways. The books of particular significance, due to inscriptions, annotations, etc., have been kept with the collection and are listed under Appendix I. Books that became part of the general collection of the Library of Congress are listed in Appendix II. Books that were returned to the Jascha Heifetz Estate are listed in Appendix III.
The sound recording transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound division are listed here in Appendix IV.
Mark Katz and Mark Horowitz, January 1998
Organization of the Jascha Heifetz Collection
The Jascha Heifetz Collection is organized into six series:
Music
Programs
Correspondence
Photographs
Scrapbooks
Miscellaneous
http://lccn.loc.gov/2003561024
Container List
- Music, 1911-1974 (Box 1-247)
  Heifetz's personal music library includes his original compositions, arrangements and transcriptions (some of which are unpublished), his annotated parts and scores, holographs and manuscripts of many of his contemporaries, and hundreds of printed scores (at least some of which appear to have been previously owned by Joseph Achron).
  The Music series has been divided into four subseries:
  Music Composed by Jascha Heifetz
  Music Arranged and Edited by Jascha Heifetz
  Music by Other Composers
  Music Lists and Catalogs
  In using the guide to the Music, the following distinctions should be observed. Bracketed titles are uniform titles, assigned in accordance with Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules, second edition. Non-bracketed titles are shown as they appear on the music itself. Numbers in parentheses refer to the number of copies. Where no contrary information is give, music may be assumed to be printed. All of Heifetz's compositions, with the exception of the cadenzas and Theme and Variations, were published under the pseudonym of Jim Hoyl.
  - Music Composed by Jascha Heifetz, 1911-1974 (Box-folder 1/1-18)
    - Blue and sentimental, Ms. vocal and instrumental versions; Laid in: lyric sheet (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Beethoven: concerto, violin, op. 61, D major, Holograph violin score (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Brahms: concerto, violin, op. 77, D major, Holograph violin score (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Brahms: concerto, violin, op. 77, D major, Printed violin score (2) (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Mozart: concerto, violin, no. 4, K. 218, D major, Holograph violin score (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Mozart: concerto, violin, no. 4, K. 218, D major, Printed violin score (2) (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Mozart: concerto, violin, no. 5, K. 219, A major, Holograph violin score (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Paganini concerto, violin, no. 1, D major, Holograph violin score (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Forever after, Ms. piano score (Box-folder 1/6)
    - If I were you, Ms. melody sketch with harmonic indications (Box-folder 1/7)
    - If I were you, Holograph sketch of piano score (Box-folder 1/7)
    - I'm back to dreaming again, Ms. melody sketch; Laid in: lyric sheet (Box-folder 1/8)
    - In Carnegie hall, Holograph sketches of piano and vocal parts; Laid in: lyric sheet (Box-folder 1/9)
    - In Carnegie hall, Photostat of ms. piano-vocal score (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Just say so, Ms. piano score (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Midnight, Holograph sketches of piano score (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Samba diablo, Holograph piano score (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Samba diablo, Ms. piano score (Box-folder 1/12)
    - So much in love, Ms. piano-vocal score; Laid in: lyric sheet (Box-folder 1/13)
    - So much in love, Photostat of ms. (Box-folder 1/13)
    - So much in love, Printed piano-vocal score; various editions (3) (Box-folder 1/13)
    - Theme and variations, Negative photocopy of fragment holograph piano score (Box-folder 1/14)
    - When you make love to me (don't make believe), Holograph melody sketch (Box-folder 1/15)
    - When you make love to me (don't make believe), Ms. vocal score (Box-folder 1/15)
    - When you make love to me (don't make believe), Photostat of ms. vocal score (Box-folder 1/15)
    - When you make love to me (don't make believe), Printed, various editions (3) (Box-folder 1/15)
    - When you make love to me (don't make believe), Photostat of printed, various editions (3) (Box-folder 1/15)
    - When you make love to me (don't make believe), Printed band parts; Orchestration by Geo. F. Terry (Box-folder 1/16)
    - When you make love to me (don't make believe), Printed band parts; Orchestration by Paul Weirick (Box-folder 1/17)
    - [Sketches], Warner's spiral manuscript book; holograph sketches (Box-folder 1/18)
    - [Sketches], Schirmer's wire bound manuscript music writing book; holograph sketches (Box-folder 1/18)
    - [Sketches], [Miscellaneous sketches]; 33 leaves holograph sketches; includes typed page of lyric: harmonie du soir (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Music Arranged and Edited by Jascha Heifetz (Box-folder 1/19-21, Box-folder 15/1, Box 2-14)
    - Composers
      - Achron, Joseph
        - Hebrew melody, Piano-violin score and part; 2 copies (Box-folder 1/19)
        - Hebrew dance, Piano-violin score and part; Original edition with Heifetz's annotations (Box-folder 1/20)
        - Hebrew dance, Piano-violin score and part; Heifetz as editor (Box-folder 1/20)
        - Hebrew lullaby, Piano-violin score and part; Original edition with Heifetz's annotations (Box-folder 1/21)
        - Hebrew lullaby, Piano-violin score and part; Edition Heifetz as editor (Box-folder 1/21)
        - From the children's suite, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano score (Box-folder 2/1)
        - From the children's suite, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 2/1)
        - Suite en style ancien, op. 21, Piano-violin score and part (Box-folder 2/2)
      - Aguirre, Julián
        - Huella, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 2/3)
        - Huella, Photocopy of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 2/3)
        - Huella, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 2/3)
      - Albéniz, Isaac
        - Sevilla, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score, in ink (Box-folder 2/4)
        - Sevilla, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score, in pencil (Box-folder 2/4)
        - Sevilla, Printed piano-violin score and part; Various editions (3) (Box-folder 2/4)
        - Navarra, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 2/5)
        - Navarra, Ms. piano-violin score (Box-folder 2/5)
        - Navarra, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 2/5)
        - El Puerto, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 2/6)
        - El Puerto, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 2/6)
      - Alkan, Charles-Valentin
        - Barcarolle, op. 65, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 2/7)
        - Barcarolle, op. 65, Photostat and negative photostat of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 2/7)
        - Barcarolle, op. 65, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 2/7)
      - Anonymous
        - Deep river, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 2/8)
        - Deep river, Photostat of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 2/8)
        - Deep river, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 2/8)
        - Soviet hymn, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 2/9)
      - Arensky, Anton
        - Tempo di valse, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 2/10)
        - Tempo di valse, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 2/10)
      - Bach, Johann Sebastian
        - Prelude (partita III), Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score and part (Box-folder 3/1)
        - Prelude (partita III), Photostat of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score and part (Box-folder 3/1)
        - Prelude (partita III), Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 3/1)
        - Gavotte and musette, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 3/2)
        - Gavotte and musette, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 3/2)
        - Sarabande, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 3/3)
        - Sarabande, Ms. piano-violin score (Box-folder 3/3)
        - Sarabande, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 3/3)
        - 2 gavottes, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 3/4)
        - 2 gavottes, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 3/4)
        - Sarabande (from English Suite No. 6), Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 3/5)
        - Sarabande (from English Suite No. 6), Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 3/5)
        - Air (from suite No. 3), Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score; Date: October 31, 1936 (Box-folder 3/6)
        - Air (from suite No. 3), Photostat of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score; Date: October 31, 1936 (Box-folder 3/6)
        - Air (from suite No. 3), Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score dated October 31, 1946; Date: October 31, 1946 (Box-folder 3/6)
        - Air (from suite No. 3), Photostat of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score; Date: October 31, 1946 (Box-folder 3/6)
        - Air (from suite No. 3), Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 3/6)
        - Prelude #8, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 3/7)
        - Prelude #8, Photostat of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 3/7)
      - Bax, Arnold
        - Mediterranean, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 3/8)
        - Mediterranean, Photostat of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 3/8)
        - Mediterranean, Printed piano-violin score and part; various editions (4) (Box-folder 3/8)
      - Beethoven, Ludwig van
        - [Concerto, violin, op. 61, D major; Cadenza by Auer; arr. by Heifetz], Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) violin score (Box-folder 3/9)
        - [Concerto, violin, op. 61, D major; Cadenza by Auer; arr. by Heifetz], Photocopy of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) violin score (Box-folder 3/9)
        - Contradance, Photostat of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 3/10)
        - Contradance, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 3/10)
        - Folk Dance, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 3/11)
        - Folk Dance, Photostat of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 3/11)
        - Folk Dance, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 3/11)
        - Minuet (D major), Holgraph piano-violin score (Box-folder 3/12)
        - Minuet (D major), Photostat of holgraph piano-violin score (Box-folder 3/12)
        - Minuet (D major), Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 3/12)
      - Borodin, Alexander
        - Sérénade, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 3/13)
        - Sérénade, Photostat of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 3/13)
        - Sérénade, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 3/13)
      - Brahms, Johannes
        - Contemplation, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 4/1)
        - Contemplation, Photostat of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 4/1)
        - Contemplation, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 4/1)
        - Hungarian Dance No. 7, Ms. full score (Box-folder 4/2)
        - Hungarian Dance No. 7, Ms. parts (Box-folder 4/2)
        - Hungarian Dance No. 7, Printed piano-violin score and part (Box-folder 4/3)
      - Castelnuovo-Tedesco, Mario
        - Sea murmurs, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 4/4)
        - Sea murmurs, Photostat of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 4/4)
        - Sea murmurs, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 4/4)
        - Figaro!, Piano-violin score and part; edited by Heifetz; Adapted from Rossini's "Barber of Seville" (Box-folder 4/5)
        - The lark, Castelnuovo-Tedesco's holograph piano-violin score and violin part with Heifetz's annotations; Printed, tan cover (Box-folder 4/6)
        - The lark, Photostat of Castelnuovo-Tedesco's holograph piano-violin score and violin part with Heifetz's annotations; Printed, gray cover (Box-folder 4/6)
        - Ritmo di tango, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 4/7)
        - Ritmo di tango, Photostat of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 4/7)
        - Ritmo di tango, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 4/7)
        - Tango, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) in pencil of piano-violin score (Box-folder 4/8)
        - Tango, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) in ink of piano-violin score (Box-folder 4/8)
        - Tango, Printed, various editions (3) (Box-folder 4/8)
      - Chopin, Frederic
        - [Nocturne, op. 55, no. 2, E-flat major], Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 4/9)
        - [Nocturne, op. 55, no. 2, E-flat major], Photostat of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 4/9)
        - [Nocturne, op. 55, no. 2, E-flat major], Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 4/9)
      - Debussy, Claude
        - Il pleure dans mon coeur, Printed piano-violin score; Arranged by Arthur Hartmann; Extensive alterations by Heifetz (Box-folder 4/10)
        - Beau Soir, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 4/11)
        - Beau Soir, Printed piano-violin score and part; Various editions (3) (Box-folder 4/11)
        - Chevelure, La, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 4/12)
        - Chevelure, La, Photostat of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 4/12)
        - Chevelure, La, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 4/12)
        - Golliwogg's cake-walk, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 5/1)
        - Golliwogg's cake-walk, Photostat of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 5/1)
        - Golliwogg's cake-walk, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 5/1)
        - Harmonie du soir, Photostat of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 5/2)
        - L'après midi d'un faune (extrait du prélude), Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 5/3)
        - L'après midi d'un faune (extrait du prélude), Printed piano-violin score and part; Various editions (4) (Box-folder 5/4)
        - Minstrels, Printed piano-violin score; Arranged by Claude Debussy; Extensive alterations by Heifetz (Box-folder 5/5)
        - La puerta del vino, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 5/6)
        - La puerta del vino, Photostat and negative photostat of arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score (Box-folder 5/6)
        - La puerta del vino, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 5/6)
      - Dinicu, Grigoras
        - Hora staccato, Composer's holograph(?) piano score; Letter from Dinicu laid in (Box-folder 5/7)
        - Hora staccato, Photocopy and negative photocopy of composer's holograph(?) piano score; Letter from Dinicu laid in (Box-folder 5/7)
        - Hora staccato, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score, in pencil (Box-folder 5/8)
        - Hora staccato, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-violin score, in ink (Box-folder 5/8)
        - Hora staccato, Copyist ms. of piano-violin score and violin part (Box-folder 5/8)
        - Hora staccato, Printed, various editions (9) (Box-folder 5/9)
        - Hora staccato, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-cello score (Box-folder 5/10)
        - Hora staccato, Printed, various editions (?) (Box-folder 5/10)
        - Hora staccato, Arranger's holograph (Heifetz) piano-clarinet (B-flat tenor saxophone) score (Box-folder 5/11)
        - Hora staccato, Printed piano-violin score and part (2) (Box-folder 5/11)